<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The characters or pourtraicts of the present court of France wherein is described the king, the princes, the generals and the principal ministers of state &amp;c. / written originally in French ; made English by J.B., Gent.</title>
            <title>Divers portraits. English</title>
            <author>Montpensier, Anne-Marie-Louise d'Orléans, duchesse de, 1627-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51200</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2507</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18747</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12171331</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12171331</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55404</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51200)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55404)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 112:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The characters or pourtraicts of the present court of France wherein is described the king, the princes, the generals and the principal ministers of state &amp;c. / written originally in French ; made English by J.B., Gent.</title>
                  <title>Divers portraits. English</title>
                  <author>Montpensier, Anne-Marie-Louise d'Orléans, duchesse de, 1627-1693.</author>
                  <author>Bulteel, John, fl. 1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 135 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for Thomas Palmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Divers portraits.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Anne-Marie-Louise, duchesse de Montpensier; the translation is doubtfully ascribed to John Bulteel. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  Court and courtiers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55404:1"/>
            <p>THE CHARACTERS OR POURTRAICTS OF Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> COURT OF FR<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>NCE:</p>
            <p>Wherein is deſcribed Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, the Princes, the Generals, and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Miniſters of State,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written Originally in French.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by J
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for Thomas Palmer, at the Crown in <hi>Westminſter-hall.</hi> 1668.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:55404:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He French Nation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at preſent the most conſiderable A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors upon the great Theatre of the World, their Vast Deſignes and Notable Progreſs having made them become the chief Subjects of most mens daily Diſcourſe; I thought it not amiſs, until a more perfect Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion comes to our hands, to give in ſhort the Names and Characters of the principal Perſons, drawn by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Country-man of their own, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aithfully copied in this Rough-draught, where you will finde a brief account of that King, thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:55404:3"/>Princes, Generals and States-men who are now ſo acti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and eager in the purſuit of Conquests. If this be received with any kindneſs, I may perhaps draw aſide the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, ſhew the Scenes, and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately deſcribe the precedent and following Champagnes, with all the Contrivances, Turns, Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, and Windings up of every Act as they ſhall ſucceed; which how it will conclude, is the enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, concern, and expectation of all <hi>Europe,</hi> amongst whom our Intereſt is not ſo little, but we ought to inform our ſelves of all the Particulars: to which if this contribute in the least, I have my Ends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Farewel.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:55404:3"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of books lately Printed, and are to be ſold by
<hi>Thomas Palmer,</hi> at the ſigne of the Crown in
<hi>Westminster-hall.</hi> 1668.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THe Characters and Pourtraicts of the preſent Court of
<hi>France:</hi> deſcribing the King, Princes, Miniſters of State, and others, in 8.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Rome exactly deſcribed:</hi> or, a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the ſtate of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> made at the late Council of
<hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadi,</hi> in two curious Diſcourſes: by the moſt Excellent, the Lord <hi>Angelo Corrare,</hi> Ambaſſadour from the moſt Serene Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique of <hi>Venice</hi> to Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> 7. Tranſlated out of ſcalian by <hi>John Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teel</hi> Gent. in large 8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Spare minutes:</hi> or, Reſolved Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and Premedicated Reſolutions, by <hi>Arthur Warwick,</hi> in 24.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Eſſays and Counſels, Civil <pb facs="tcp:55404:4"/>and Moral: whereunto is newly added A Fable of the Colours of Good and Evil: by the Right Honourable Sir <hi>Fr. Bacon,</hi> Lord <hi>Verulam,</hi> Viſcount
<hi>S. Alban,</hi> in large 12.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Flagelum,</hi> or the Life and death of <hi>O. Cromwel,</hi> from his Birth to his Burial. With an exact Account of his Policies and Succeſſes: with a Diſcovery of his private and publike actions, not till now made publike. Impartially written by <hi>James Heath</hi> Gent. in large 8.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>The Engliſh Rogue deſcribed,</hi> in the Life of
<hi>Meriton Latroon</hi> a Witty Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant: being a Compleat Diſcovery of the moſt eminent Cheats of both Sexes: in large 8.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Cupids Courtſhip:</hi> or, the Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Marriage between the Godd of Love and <hi>Pſyche,</hi> in a Poem, by the ſame ingenious Author, in 8.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Venus Cabinet unlocked,</hi> and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures chief Miracles and Rarities laid open: being a Curious Collection out of the two eminent Phyſicians, <hi>Levinus Lemnius,</hi> and <hi>Sinibaldus,</hi> and others: made Engliſh by <hi>Rob. Miller</hi> M. D. in 12.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>The compleat Sollicitor:</hi> perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb facs="tcp:55404:4"/>his duty, and teaching his Clyent to run through his own Buſineſs, as well in his Majeſties ſuperior Courts at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> as in the Mayors Court, Court of Huſtings, Court of Marſhalſey, and other inferiour Courts both in the City of <hi>London</hi> and elſewhere: the like not formerly extant: written by <hi>R. T.</hi> Gent. in 80.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The firſt &amp; ſecond Part of <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and Advice to Builders,</hi> for the choice of their Surveyors, Clerks of their Works, Bricklayers, Maſons, Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With ſeveral Letters to his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty, his Royal Highneſs, Prince
<hi>Rupert,</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle,</hi> and other Lords, Knights and Gentlemen of the Realm, concerning the three chief Principles of Magnificent Building, <hi>viz.</hi> Solidity, Conveniency, and Ornament. Written by Sir
<hi>Balthazar Gerbier Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nilly,</hi> Knight, in 8. A Work very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for all thoſe that are concerned in rebuilding the citie of
<hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>Don Juan Lamberto:</hi> or, a Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Hiſtory of our late Times: wherein the Contrivances of the late Rebels un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Names are Jovially diſcovered, <pb facs="tcp:55404:5"/>and to the life diſplayed: in two parts. By <hi>John Philips</hi> Gent. in 4.</p>
            <p n="12">12. The Royal Game of the <hi>Ombre,</hi> written at the requeſt of divers Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſons, by <hi>R. F.</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> in 8.</p>
            <p>At the ſame Shop alſo, any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may have Hiſtories, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, Plays, or other Books, lent them to read; or any that have Books to ſell, may there have Money for them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="characters">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55404:5"/>
            <head>THE Characters and Pourtraicts OF THE COURT OF FRANCE.</head>
            <p>FOr the better underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Affairs and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of
<hi>France,</hi> it is fit to know thoſe perſons that Govern, and ſuch as are any thing conſiderable, either for their Offices or Quality; And therefore we ſhall begin with the <pb facs="tcp:55404:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55404:6"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:55404:7"/>Characters of thoſe that are moſt Eminent and Illuſtrious. To which ſhall be added their ſeveral Offices and Functions. We will diſtinguiſh the Order of the Kings Council, and the ſeveral Employments in the War. And laſtly, treat curſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Revenues whereby all theſe ſubſiſt.</p>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:55404:7"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict OF THE KING, And all His Preeminences.</head>
               <p>THe Moſt Chriſtian King is the Eldeſt Son of the Chriſtian Church, by the conſent of the States of Chriſtendom, and the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the very Infidels themſelves, who in their Treaties between <hi>Henry</hi> the IV, and the Grand <hi>Signior,</hi> gave him the Title of the greateſt <hi>Monarch</hi> of the Chriſtian Faith; really Soveraign, Abſolute, and Immortal in his own <pb n="4" facs="tcp:55404:8"/>Kingdom of
<hi>France.</hi> The ſucceſſion is by a Natural Right, and by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the <hi>Salique Law,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veys it from Male to Male, as they are neareſt in Blood, to the exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Females, who have ever contented themſelves with the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of being Dames of <hi>France,</hi> and ſubmitted to the Kings will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; from whom they receive ſuch advantages as he is willing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow, according to the greatneſs of his Dignity, and the intereſt of his Power. <hi>Childebert</hi> the Firſt of the firſt Race, was preferred before the Daughters of <hi>Lewis</hi> the II, without any oppoſition againſt that Election. <hi>Philip</hi> the IV. of
<hi>Valois</hi> was preferred before <hi>Iſabella</hi> Daughter of
<hi>France,</hi> and Queen of <hi>England. Lewis</hi> the XII. after
<hi>Charles</hi> the VIII. <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt next to him, and
<hi>Henry</hi> the IV. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Henry</hi> the III.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:55404:8"/>
               <p>The preſent King is the Son and Succeſſor to
<hi>Lewis</hi> the XIII, Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Henry</hi> the IV, deſcended from
<hi>Anthony</hi> of <hi>Burbon</hi> King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> and from
<hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> fourth Son of <hi>Lewis</hi> the IX. All his Genealogy derives from <hi>Hugh Capet,</hi> the firſt King of the third Race. He is of ſo handſome a ſhape and mine, that <hi>Don Juan</hi> of
<hi>Auſtria</hi> ſeeing him paſs by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any attendance, and the Queen having ſaid to him, <hi>Do you know that this is the King of France?</hi> Replyed, <hi>Although I am yet unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with him, yet Madam I was perſwaded in mind that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that quality, looking upon him as the beſt accompliſh'd Frenchman, and moſt worthy to Reign over them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He will be ſole Maſter, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure to be governed by any other; he is bold, haughty, and <pb n="6" facs="tcp:55404:9"/>fearleſs; ſpeaks but little, and well to purpoſe; conſtant in his reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, very ſecret and judicious. The <hi>Portugal</hi> Ambaſſadour told him once, <hi>Sir, I ſhall diſpatch this buſineſs with your Miniſters. I have no Miniſters, Sir,</hi> replied the King, <hi>you mean our inferiour Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</hi> At their return from <hi>Lions,</hi> the Cardinals having ſet ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons aſide, for whom the King had a particular eſteem, he ſaid in the preſence of ſeveral of his Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who have often affirmed it to me, <hi>The Cardinal does all what he pleaſes, and I ſuffer it, becauſe of the good ſervices he has rendred me; but my turn will come to be Maſter one day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He covets to imitate his Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, nay, even to ſurpaſs him, as himſelf once teſtified to <hi>Monſieur de Paris,</hi> who was diſcourſing of it: <hi>The King my Grandfather did <pb n="7" facs="tcp:55404:9"/>many great things, and has left ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great things to do; if it pleaſe God to let me live twenty years lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, I may, perhaps, do as great, if not greater things then he.</hi> There was never any Prince that knew better how to make himſelf be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected then this, nor to keep eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one within his duty and diſtance; all which he effects without any noiſe, or the leaſt appearance of clamour. I have alſo been a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his patience, upon a trial which would have loſt it ſelf in any other perſon. One afternoon at
<hi>Fountainbleau</hi> he had given order to his Coachman to have his
<hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſche</hi> there about four a clock, to go a hunting; the whole Court was in a readineſs for the ſport, and it had ſtruck four a long while be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the Clock, yet the Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Coach came not. The King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf came often to the Balcone to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55404:10"/>look for him: but it was on the ſtroke of five before the Coach ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared. The King going into the <hi>Caleſche,</hi> ſaid,
<hi>Coachman, I told you I would have the Coach at four a Clock. Sir,</hi> replied the man, who had, it may be, tipled the time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, <hi>It is but four now.</hi> The King, who knew the contrary, ſaid no more, but, <hi>Drive along, that's your beſt way, and never commit the like agen.</hi> It is averred, that he par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons the firſt offence; ſeverely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves the ſecond; but at third he turns them away without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. He requires an inviolable execution of all his Orders: when he had given command to ſeize on <hi>Monſieur Fouquet,</hi> at his coming forth from the Council,
<hi>Monſieur</hi> at <hi>Artagnan</hi> by accident miſs'd him, for he had not taken his own Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan, but retired in another into a little Alley, to give Audience to <pb n="9" facs="tcp:55404:10"/>ſome certain people. <hi>Monſieur d'Artagnan</hi> very much ſurprized, and fearing <hi>Monſieur Fouquet</hi> might have ſome intelligence of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and make a ſecret eſcape, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſent a Muſquettier to give the King notice he was not to be found. The King was then wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Letter about the detection of the ſaid Treaſurer to the Queen-Mother at that time at <hi>Fountain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleau;</hi> and the Souldier having told him the news, without naming any body, <hi>Go,</hi> ſaid the King, <hi>and tell Artagnan that he muſt be found! and I ſhall find him well enough!</hi> And then turning himſelf towards the Prince,
<hi>'Tis</hi> Fouquet, <hi>Couſen, that I intend to ſeize upon, becauſe be withholds all my Revenues, and puts me to a thouſand troubles to get a little money of him, of which he never gives me any account.</hi> The Prince, and all the other Lords <pb n="10" facs="tcp:55404:11"/>were much aſtoniſhed at this, they knowing nothing of it; but every one commended the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and reſolution of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
               <p>He is very temperate, and was never known to give himſelf over to the leaſt exceſs, amidſt the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his delights and pleaſures, no more then he does to his anger, for all his Power and Authority; which plainly ſhews he is a perfect Maſter over himſelf, not tainted with any paſſion that might eclipſe his other excellent Qualities: Or if there be any Objection againſt him, it is his Frugality; but that is inherent to the Family of the <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons,</hi> who have ever been noted for great heapers up of Riches. But this reproach he hath wiped off ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry judiciouſly, by ſaying publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>My Subjects will, I hope, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider me as a young married man, who <pb n="11" facs="tcp:55404:11"/>is about ſetling his Family, and ought to take care of furniſhing himſelf plentifully; but within a while they ſhall find the effects of it; for I have a regard to them as well as to my ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He underſtands all his Exerciſes to the beſt advantage, eſpecially the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> and the Art of <hi>Fortification.</hi> There is no Officer can command his Troops ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, and with ſo much ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. He rides the Great Horſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gracefully and skilfully; and can uſe any Weapon with as much dexterity as any Maſter of thoſe Sciences. He Dances admirably; and though he wear ſometimes a diſguize, yet his Majeſtick Garb and Ayr does ſoon diſcover him. He laughs but ſeldom, and with much moderation; and the Jeſt muſt be very witty and well placed to gain his approbation, however o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eſteem it.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:55404:12"/>
               <p>In fine, it muſt needs be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that this Great King hath all the Vertues and Qualifications neceſſary to command ſo vaſt a Kingdom as his is: nay, ſo eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is he endued with them, that he is worthy of the whole Worlds Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, there being nothing wanting towards it, but his being fully known to all Nations, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt would be charmed by his incomparable Vertues, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſubmit themſelves to the mildeſt and beſt-regulated Empire that was ever yet known to this Great Univerſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:55404:12"/>
               <head>Of the Kings Family.</head>
               <p>THe wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> upon his firſt advancement to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Crown, built him a Houſe, ſuch as the Scripture repreſents to us of ſo marvellous a Structure, that it invited the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> to come and admire both its great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and glory: and of this puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant King of <hi>Lillies,</hi> under the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of an Illuſtrious Woman, one who is worthy of the Title of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of the greateſt Monarch in the World, I think we may ſay the ſame, if not more, who Reigns at preſent with ſo much ſplendour, through the Care and Noble Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of that Regent who gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him during his minority, and hath ſeated him on the Throne with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55404:13"/>ſo much Pomp and Majeſty, after ſhe had beſtowed an univerſal Peace. The ſtately building of the <hi>Louvre</hi> continued with ſo much heat, beſides the admirable Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of a thouſand other Royal and Publick Buildings; the Iuſtre of the Throne ſuſtained with ſo much Judgement; the admirable Conduct in the eſtabliſhment and reglement of the Royal Family; the preſent re-union of the Princes; the general Peace, which ſpreads a joy over all the Earth: In fine, the auguſt and glorious preſence of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Gift of God,</hi> hath not only attracted a High-born and Wiſe Queen to come and admire his Greatneſs; but likewiſe tempts the greateſt and nobleſt part of all <hi>Europe</hi> beſides to behold him, whom Fame hath noiſed all abroad. All theſe, I ſay, are Subjects ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to be compared to all the <pb n="15" facs="tcp:55404:13"/>Wonders of Antiquity, and to make us repeat that paſſage in Scripture, <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, That</hi> Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>in all his glory was never equal to this Triumphant Monarch.</hi> The Deſign or Model of the <hi>Louvre</hi> is to make four ſpacious Courts, where ſix thouſand men may be drawn up in
<hi>Battalia:</hi> and beſides the regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity of the Buildings, and their ingenious Architecture, which is ſuppoſed ſhall ſurpaſs all that the height of Art or Greatneſs hath yet produced in the reſt of the World; They are contriving Apartments convenient and ſufficient to lodge the whole Royal Family, beſides all the Principal Officers of the Crown. Thus the Grandeur and Magnificence of the Court will be more conſpicuous in ſuch an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblage, then now as it is divided. In the mean while, till that Work be compleated, I ſhall trace out a <pb n="16" facs="tcp:55404:14"/>ſlight draught of it, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of ſuch as deſire the knowledge of it.</p>
               <p>This numerous and pompous Train belonging to his Majeſty, may be comprehended under theſe three Heads: The multiplicity of the Princes, or ſuch as the neceſſary Offices require, or thoſe whom for his Majeſties pleaſure and for the Ornament of the Court are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly attending. Thoſe that are moſt fixed, like ſome brighter Stars ſtill following the Sun, are the Queen, the Princes of the Blood, and ſome other forraign Princes, who prefer the Honour of being under this Empire, above the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of other Dominions, or the ſubjection of other Monarchs: and ſo highly do our Princes value their condition, though but Subjects in this Court, that thoſe of the Blood Royal never did, nor ever will give
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55404:14"/>precedency to any other Subject Prince on Earth, nor to any of his Ambaſſadours, only to a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign when preſent.</p>
               <p>We have a Cloud of Examples, and one very freſh, between
<hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> to whom his Royal Highneſs would not give the right hand, even when he came to his own Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; which abſolutely hindred the interview betwixt thoſe two Princes. It is true, that <hi>Monſieur</hi> yielded to an Equality with the Prince of <hi>Denmark;</hi> but it was in reſpect of the infallible pretences he hath to be king of his Native Country, which is reckoned a
<hi>Soveraignty.</hi> But this muſt be noted, that he would not however yield to any more then an Equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and for this cauſe they never came together. This preeminence of the Princes of the Blood ſhines <pb n="18" facs="tcp:55404:15"/>brighter now, after the long conteſt betwixt the Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Lorraine</hi> and ours, which but a few days ſince was ſetled after this manner. During the former Reigns of <hi>Henry</hi> the II,
<hi>Charles</hi> the IX, and <hi>Henry</hi> the III, the Houſe of
<hi>Guiſe</hi> had acquired ſo much cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in the Court of
<hi>France,</hi> that beſides that they were become the abſolute Maſters of all Affairs under the Regency of <hi>Catharine</hi> of <hi>Medices,</hi> they had flatter'd themſelves with ſome pretenſions to the Crown; a certain Canon of <hi>Verdun</hi> publiſhed in a Printed Book of his, that they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who was deprived by the Eſtates of the right of Succeſſion to the Crown of
<hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Hugh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pett</hi> was ſubſtituted in his ſtead. And though this Genealogy was falſe, as divers Authors have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55404:15"/>in clearing out their deſcent from the Counts of
<hi>Alſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia;</hi> Nevertheleſs the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> who were very potent in the Kingdom, made uſe of this advantage: for the neceſſity of affairs, and the fear of their Authority, having obliged <hi>Henry</hi> the III. to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend that the Princes of the Blood ſhould yield the right hand to the Chief of the houſe of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and that the younger Sons of the Houſe of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſhould in the ſame manner give the upper hand to the Princes of the Blood of <hi>France;</hi> Our Princes have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver obſerved this order, but op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it very vigorouſly, till ſuch time as the King by full Power and Authority, and knowing the Juſtice of their Cauſe, hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, That ever hereafter, all the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Princes, and even the Head of that Family, ſhould give <pb n="20" facs="tcp:55404:16"/>place to the Princes of the Blood; and to this purpoſe he ſent an Order by
<hi>Monſieur Tellier</hi> to <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Guiſe,</hi> who is here the Chief or Head of that Family, to go and give a viſit to the Prince, and to give place to him upon all occaſions, yea, even in his own Houſe; and to obſerve the very ſame towards all the reſt of the Princes of the Blood: Which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was immediately executed by <hi>Monſieur de Guiſe,</hi> and afterwards by all the reſt of that Family. There was another conteſt of Precedency between Strangers, or Forraign Princes, and the Dukes and Pairs. Theſe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a Right as well as the Princes of the Blood, to go before for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Princes, eſpecially at great Solemnities, where they pretend to repreſent Soveraign Perſons by vertue of their Dignities, which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55404:16"/>are undoubtedly the firſt and higheſt in the Kingdom.
'Tis true, they have heretofore been Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns, and yet always Subjects or Vaſſals to the King, being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to render homage for what they held of the Crown. Their riſe is attributed to <hi>Hugh Capett;</hi> for that Prince, to make himſelf King, agreed to beſtow his Dutchies and Pairies to thoſe great Lords who were moſt able to oppoſe him in his advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Throne. This made them ſo potent, that having once declared to the Duke of
<hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> that he could not approve of his intents of making War up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> and the Duke little regarding his reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the King bidding ſome body aſk him, <hi>Who it was had made him Duke of Aquitain?</hi> He replied with much haughtineſs,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55404:17"/>
                  <hi>Thoſe that made him King.</hi> And although they are now perfectly ſubmitted to Regal Authority, yet they are careful of preſerving the remainders of their Grandeur towards forraign Princes; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon many of them would not appear at the entrance of the King and Queen into <hi>Paris</hi> after their Marriage, becauſe the Count <hi>de Soiſſons,</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Savoy,</hi> would not yield them the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency and rank they claim in all Royal Ceremonies, by vertue of their Dignities. But what great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſoever theſe Nobles of <hi>France</hi> do attribute to themſelves, yet there are others that do contend with them for precedency, and go already in equal rank, having no leſs Authority in the Kingdom then they. Our Kings, to maintain an equal poiſe and temperament in the State, have always equally <pb n="23" facs="tcp:55404:17"/>conſidered Valour and Juſtice, and for this reſpect have made Gentlemen of the Robe, as well as of the Sword, having allowed them the ſame priviledges, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages and immunities, without any diſtinction; it being indubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, that a State conſiſts equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Power and Juſtice: the Sword-men however have ſtill attributed ſomething of preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence to themſelves; but thoſe of the long Robe, have wiſely taken the Superiority on their parts, of which they do not vaunt, though in effect they diſpoſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely of the Eſtates, Lives and Honour of the other, by an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Crown, wherewith they ſhelter themſelves, ſitting upon the <hi>Royal Lillies,</hi> as Judges of the greateſt Peers and Princes of the Blood, who are bound to ſtand to their Sentence, and <pb n="24" facs="tcp:55404:18"/>come in at their Summons, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for themſelves. I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber an Example during the laſt troubles, in the perſon of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur</hi> the Prince; they had given him ſome cauſe to apprehend he might be again confined, though but newly out of Priſon; which occaſioned his retreat to S. <hi>Maur.</hi> The Parliament deputed two Counſellors to go to this Prince, and invite him to come and ſhew the Reaſons for his retiremens, to the Parliament. He comes accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with his Royal Highneſs, the Prince of <hi>Conty,</hi> the Princes of <hi>Nemours, Guiſe,</hi> and other Lords that aſſembled themſelves. There the firſt Preſident addreſſing his Speech to the Prince, boldly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd him for withdrawing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf tumultuouſly from
<hi>Paris,</hi> and told him, <hi>That he would make him reſponſable for all the diſorders <pb n="25" facs="tcp:55404:18"/>that ſhould happen, thoſe actions of his being but like the Alarms to a Civil War, during the Kings Minority; it being well known at Court, that he kept Secret Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence with the Kings Enemies, and cauſed ſeveral places to be forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, amongst which</hi> Bellegarde <hi>was one.</hi> To which the Prince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, with as much heat,
<hi>That if any diſorders did happen in the Kingdom, themſelves would be the only cauſers of it; to which they had already given birth. That for his part, he deteſted the deſigne of any ſuch diſturbance in his Soul; and for the correſpondence they mentioned he held with the Enemy, it was falſe; nor could they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the leaſt Witneſs againſt him; there being as little verity alſo in what they alledged touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Bellegarde, <hi>which they parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly objected; concerning which, <pb n="26" facs="tcp:55404:19"/>he vow'd and proteſted both to his Royal Highneſs and the Court, that there had not been one ſhovel full of Earth removed to any ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</hi> Upon which the firſt Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent with as much confidence as he began, reſumed his Speech, and told him, <hi>That indeed his words were good and plauſible, but yet many times mens words and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions look contrary ways, as his were ſuſpected to do;</hi> and then proceeded to reprove him in theſe terms: <hi>It is very laudable to ſee the Prince of</hi> Conde <hi>keep within his Palace in the</hi> Fauxburgh <hi>Saint</hi> Germaines, <hi>and not vouchſafe to go over the new Bridge to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the King his Lord and Maſter. This looks like an intrenching and barricading ones ſelf on the other ſide of the River againſt the</hi> Louvre; <hi>and what will ſtrangers ſay, Sir, when they hear of ſuch <pb n="27" facs="tcp:55404:19"/>proceedings of the Prince of</hi> Conde
<hi>towards the King?</hi> The Prince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied again as ſmartly as at the beginning: <hi>That his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs had given him caution not to do it, and would not undertake for the ſecurity of his perſon, the Cardinal</hi> Mazarine <hi>ruling ſtill in the hearts of the Court, where his Enemies were yet the ſtrongeſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and threatned him with a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond impriſonment. But that he ſtill muſt attribute all the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and diſturbances that might happen, to their negligence, unleſs they would acquaint the King and Queen with his juſt Reaſons, and moſt humble Remonſtrances.</hi> This conteſt betwixt the Preſidents and the Dukes and Pairs of <hi>France</hi> for Precedency, hath been of late ſtarted up more then ever, upon ſome accidents hapning in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Proceſſion. One of theſe laſt <pb n="28" facs="tcp:55404:20"/>Holydays, the Preſident <hi>de Meſmes</hi> Footmen, being the more nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, took place of the Duke of
<hi>Briſac</hi>'s, upon which there en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued a great quarrel and debate; but the Duke's were in fine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to yield to the number and ſtrength of the others; upon which the Duke's preferred their complaints, with a great deal of heat, having demanded for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice againſt them; each of them made their own defence, and the Duke's have newly produced their <hi>Manifeſto,</hi> and preſented it to the King to have a deciſion of it. It is ſaid that his Majeſty goes in perſon the next week to the Parliament for this end, and to give order to the Chancellour to collect firſt the <hi>Votes</hi> of the Dukes and Pairs before thoſe of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents. But others that are very clear-ſighted, do believe that the <pb n="29" facs="tcp:55404:20"/>buſineſs will be thus accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; That the Preſidents ſhall have precedency in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but ſhall any where elſe give it to all Dukes and Pairs, eſpecially at Extraordinary Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and Triumphant Showes, where the Sword ſeems to claim a Right above the long Robe. Of this we expect the Iſſue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:55404:21"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict Of the QUEEN-MOTHER.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANna Maria Mauritia</hi> of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> Daughter of
<hi>Philip</hi> the III. King of <hi>Spain,</hi> was married to <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIII. King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Navarre.</hi> The Marſhall <hi>d' Ancre</hi> made up this match, and carried the King to <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> to that end, whileſt an Army lay amuſing the Princes of the League in
<hi>Champagne.</hi> She was married many years before ſhe had any children, but at length ſhe brought forth this King, and <hi>Monſieur</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55404:21"/>having never had any Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or other Children then theſe two. After the death of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIII, ſhe was declared
<hi>Queen Regent,</hi> and made uſe of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and adminiſtration of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> during the time of her Regency and the Kings mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. The beginning of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery was both peaceable, and happy enough: for, to gain the amity and good will of the great ones, he ſhewed the Kings fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours upon them with an open hand indifferently, being conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to engage them to be of his party, that they ſhould ſhare with him in his Maſters Grace and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. He endeavoured like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe at firſt to ſtrengthen himſelf with ſome conſiderable Alliance; and to this purpoſe he ſent for ſome of his Nephews and Nieces, and other Relations, whom he <pb n="32" facs="tcp:55404:22"/>cauſed to be bred up at Court af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the French Mode and Air, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hopes of future Grandeur. But we ſhall mention this Miniſter in a Chapter apart, which ſhall deſcribe both his Perſon and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct.</p>
               <p>The Queen-Mother is a good and vertuous Princeſs, of a paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique ſpirit, and an exemplary Piety. She wants neither for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution nor conduct in great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, nor for good will towards the publick Intereſt. Her great courage was apparent during the troubles of her Regency: when ſhe reſolved to make uſe of her power againſt
<hi>Paris,</hi> and asked the Prince upon his return from the battail, <hi>Will you ſuffer them to affront the Regal Authority?</hi> (meaning the buſineſs of the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricadoes, when they would abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely have
<hi>Monſieur Brouſſel</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed <pb n="33" facs="tcp:55404:22"/>leaſed upon their popular inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection) <hi>This violence concerns you,</hi> continued ſhe. To whom the Prince replied, <hi>Madam, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, this Sword of mine is ever at his Majeſties ſervice, which you may abſolutely command.</hi> She ſhewed alſo a great deal of reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in her enterprize upon the Princes, whom ſhe cauſed to be ſeized on by her Captain of the Guards; but her undaunted ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit appeared moſt eminently after the Cardinals abſence, when ſhe took the Helme of the State into her own hands, and ſteering all affairs during that hideous tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, cauſing the King to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in his Majority, after ſhe had driven the Prince into
<hi>Guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enne,</hi> and confined the Cardinal <hi>de Retz,</hi> who had been flattered with the hopes of being chief Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. In a word, ſhe appeared
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55404:23"/>to be, what ſhe really was, that is to ſay, good natur'd, and pacifick in her heart, when ſhe forgave her enemies, without the ſmalleſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment of any injury; and ſtood for Peace in deſpite of the Cardinals intentions, even ſo far as to command him to make it up for the general good of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom. She is Magnificent without exceſs, and glories in her Birth and Alliance. Her Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is more then common, and often repeated, yet without affectation or ſeverity. Her Vertue appears without any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guize, ſhe taking pleaſure to do good in the beſt manner, thereby to attract the World to follow her vertuous Examples. Shee cauſed the <hi>Val de Grace</hi> to be built for her retreat, as a holy Solitude, whither ſhe goes to ſeek her God out of the noiſe of the <pb n="35" facs="tcp:55404:23"/>Court, and the confuſion of State-Employments. She is very Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable to the poor Convents, to whom ſhe allows a comfortable ſubſiſtence; that ſo they may follow their Devotions and Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, with their harmleſs Recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations. She hath always endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to nouriſh a happy Union and Correſpondence in the Royal Family; and by her vertue main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained her ſelf as Mother to the King of <hi>France</hi> with ſo much diſcretion, that ſhe yet retains a great Authority with a potent King, and a Noble Prince, who do each of them honour her moſt entirely. She made the match be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the King and the Daughter of <hi>Spain,</hi> whoſe Father is her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; having ſetled them in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Amity, to the great content of their Subjects, and the joy of all Chriſtendom. She ſhewed a <pb n="36" facs="tcp:55404:24"/>great deal of moderation amidſt that power and plenty ſhe was Miſtreſs of; in an Age ſo corrupt and greedy of gain, that nothing is ſufficient to glut the deſires of moſt people. She alone never heaped up any Treaſure, but reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed content with what Nature, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and her Quality brought freely to her Store.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:55404:24"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict Of <hi>MONSIE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE is the Kings only Brother; a Prince well ſhaped, good natured, and very Gallant: he is not, however, ſo Majeſtick as the King; hath not that full ſtock of generous bounty, ſolidity, and haughty bravery. He is mild, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable, civil and obliging; very complaiſant to the Ladies, always gay and active, curious of rarities, and nice in his Habits and Modes, in his Furnitures and Cabinets, and very perfect in the Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55404:25"/>belonging to Architecture, the Art: of Muſick, Perſpective and Agriculture. Though this Prince hath ever ſhewed an exact ſubmiſſion to all the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and preſerved an extreme reſpect for the Queen-Mother, yet he could never be brought to favour Cardinal <hi>Mazarine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For it is reported, that the Cardinal one day at St.
<hi>Germains</hi> paſſed by him, and pulled off his Hat by way of ſalutation; he one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſt an eye upon him, but moved not at all, not ſo much as to take notice of his civility, or return the ceremony. The Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal going immediately to the Queens apartment, complained o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly to her, ſaying,
<hi>I do not know what I have done to</hi> Monſieur, <hi>that he ſhould treat me with ſo much ſcorn; I thought he had a better e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of me, having never given <pb n="39" facs="tcp:55404:25"/>him any occaſion to treat me ſo.</hi> The Queen-Mother having ſent for <hi>Monſieur,</hi> made him a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand reproaches for it, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him with ſome kinde of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, for not riſing up to the Cardinal: To which <hi>Monſieur</hi> at the inſtant replyed, <hi>Though he had been the Pope, I ſhould not have riſen to him.</hi> He was threatned to be chaſtiſed for ſaying ſo; but he explained it very handſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, telling them, <hi>One doth not uſe to riſe up to the Pope, but fall down upon ones knees before him, which I ſhould then have been obliged to do.</hi> He ever ſhewed himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe to that Miniſters proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, chiefly becauſe he did not give him enough to maintain his Family, and his other divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in that ſplendor and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence as he deſired, and as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was requiſite to his quality <pb n="40" facs="tcp:55404:26"/>of the Kings Brother. He was bred up with a great deal of fear and reſpect towards the King, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much application to learning, or knowledge in the Art of War; yet he did ſometimes ride the great Horſe, but not with ſo much aſſiduity as the King. He hath a marvelous ready wit to make reparties: a mongſt others, let this ſhow his ability, it being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what remarkable.</p>
               <p>The King took him one day to viſit the Buildings at the
<hi>Lonvre,</hi> before <hi>Monſieur Fouquet's</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace; and complaining, <hi>That he wanted money to continue that vaſt Structure; Monſieur</hi> replyed very aptly, <hi>Sir, your Majeſty muſt onely take upon you to be Super in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendent of your revenues for one year, and you will have enough to carry on your Building.</hi> He loves peace and quietneſs, ſeldom di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbing <pb n="41" facs="tcp:55404:26"/>ſturbing himſelf with the tumult and trade of War; yet he hath kept his Majeſty company, and endured all the fatigues of a long voyage, without trouble or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint. Before his Marriage he had a great deal of friendſhip for Madam <hi>de Hourdon;</hi> and the Queen, to make ſome diſcovery of his minde, told him once, <hi>That it ſeemed to her he was in love with that Lady, having ſent her a pair of Pendants worth four thouſand Crowns for a New-years gift.</hi> To which he anſwered, <hi>That for friendſhip and compaſſion, he had indeed ſome towards her, as being a poor ſtranger far from her own Country, and deſtitute of means; which were indeed the treaſons why he ſent her that Regalio.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:55404:27"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict Of the PRINCE.</head>
               <p>PRince <hi>Lewis</hi> Son of <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> deſcended from <hi>Lewis</hi> Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> younger Brother of
<hi>Henry</hi> the IV. is one of the moſt couragious and ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Captains either of this or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages, not excepting either
<hi>Alexander</hi> or <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus;</hi> being ſo fearleſs of any peril or danger, that it hath been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times judged he was rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate then valiant. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal <hi>Gaſſion,</hi> who was one of the <pb n="43" facs="tcp:55404:27"/>braveſt men of his time, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in him: the Prince, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him of his error, thought it ſufficient to let him know by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that no danger could in any attaque ſhake his great Soul. At the Battel of <hi>Rocroy,</hi> where this Prince made his firſt Eſſay, he never ſhewed the leaſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, although the beginning of it were very diſadvantagious to his party, and himſelf threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a general defeat; but he beſtirred himſelf with ſo much cagerneſs, and rallied up his broken and flying Regiments with ſo much courage and heat, and good example, that he made all the <hi>French</hi> at laſt reſolve ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to vanquiſh, or die with him. The Baron <hi>de Syrop,</hi> one of the beſt reſolved men in his Army, did ſecond him extraordinarily well in this ſight, and juſtly merited a <pb n="44" facs="tcp:55404:28"/>Marſhals Staff for that eminent ſervice; but he miſſed that due recompence, and all other advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages ſince, rather by misfortune then any want of deſert: that days actions having proclaimed his worth to all the world. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the battle of
<hi>Rocroy,</hi> which was both his maiden-attempt and Maſter-piece; He hath gained three other Victories, two in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> at <hi>Fribourgh</hi> and <hi>Nordlin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen:</hi> He alſo took <hi>Philips bourgh</hi> in eighteen days, which had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood a Royal Seige for eighteen months, and ſaved it ſelf from the proſperous valour of the Great <hi>Gustavus.</hi> The laſt battle he won was that of <hi>Lens;</hi> the joy and triumph for which Victory was ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced by the diſorder of the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricado's, where the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was in confuſion, moſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Arms, and the Kings Palace
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55404:28"/>almoſt beſieged; all which up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roar happened about
<hi>Monſieur Bronſtet,</hi> a Counſellor in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who had been that day arreſted upon his vigorous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings on ſome points in the behalf of the people. The <hi>Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> in this action plainly violated all Authority through their obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, obliging the Miniſters to ſurrender up the Priſoner, with two others who were taken with him; and in this great heat of theirs, they remained three whole days and nights in Arms; nor would they be appeaſed till he was reſtored, whom they called the Protector of the People, and had brought him back with tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph and general acclamations in the Kings own Coach.</p>
               <p>The Prince employed all his courage to revenge this ſeditious act; and his reſolve being fixt to <pb n="46" facs="tcp:55404:29"/>beſiege the City, he went out thence in the night with the whole Court, leaving thoſe that remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a horrible conſternation; but after much ado, things being brought to an accommodation, the Court returned to <hi>Paris;</hi> and the fruits of all the Princes labours came to this, that he drew the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral odium and hatred of the Citizens upon himſelf, by his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo forward and buſie to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour their chaſtiſement. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the Prince having ſerved the Court ſo faithfully on all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, thought he had reaſon to expect ſome conſiderable recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence; and being obliging, active, and reſtleſs, he after preſſed the Cardinal, in favour of ſome of his relations, for ſome Command or Office.</p>
               <p>The Cardinal thinking to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move him from any vicinity to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55404:29"/>the Court, preſents him with the Government of
<hi>Guienne</hi> in lieu of that of <hi>Burgundy;</hi> which the Prince readily gave way to, as well becauſe it is more honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as becauſe he hoped to keep the better correſpondence and intelligence with the <hi>Sieur de Marſin,</hi> Lieutenant-General in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> who was his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>But this not being enough to ſecure him from the private at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of Enemies, they aſſaulted his Coachon the <hi>Pont-Neuf</hi> in diſguiſe, ſhot into it, and wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Page, who then ſat in the Princes Seat. The Prince made a narrow and diligent ſearch after theſe Aſſaſines; and ſome jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies there were of <hi>Monſieur de Beaufort,</hi> and the Cardinal <hi>de Retz:</hi> but whilſt he was laying an Ambuſcade to intrap ſome of the <pb n="48" facs="tcp:55404:30"/>Accomplies, he never imagined they had pitched their Toils to take him, and conduct him to the
<hi>Bois de Vincennes,</hi> whither he was led Priſoner by his Majeſties Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Never did ſo great a heart ſo patiently ſubmit to confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: himſelf directed the beſt way to that place, which he had found out upon an occaſion of carrying ſome Guns thither, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the troubles at
<hi>Paris,</hi> which could not be, drawn the other way, by reaſon of the deepneſs of it.</p>
               <p>About thirteen months after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he was releaſed, upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Intrigue between the Cardinal <hi>de Retz</hi> and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: a Letter which he writ with a Back-lead-pen, and which was ſigned by the Prince of <hi>Conti</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi> his Brothers, and companions in his <pb n="49" facs="tcp:55404:30"/>reſtraint, being preſented to the Parliament, to whom it was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, did very much contribute to his releaſe. He hath ever ſince been very jealous of the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and rather adventured to withdraw himſelf into <hi>Flanders,</hi> then to fall again into his hands. But although he ever was his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, yet he never ſpake any ill of him; only he would ſometimes let his friends know he did not approve of his Conduct. He was ſaying once, <hi>That there were three perſons in</hi> France <hi>that made much noiſe; one was the Marſhal of</hi> Turenne, <hi>who was the beſt and moſt prudent Captain of thoſe times, but yet very unfortunate. Another, the Cardinal</hi> Mazarine, <hi>who was the ableſt in the World for Counſel, but the greateſt coward alive. The laſt was himſelf, who had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe two perfections, but
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:55404:31"/>yet was much happier then either of them</hi> He is now returned to his duty, and yields his obedience with ſo much ſubmiſſion and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence, that it is eaſily judged, he had no quarrel with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, but all his diſcontent aroſe from Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> with whom he was again preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled. He is Brave, Generous, Learned, and Active as any man alive, nor does he want diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on when occaſions call for it. At preſent he is very intent about the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of his Family, enquiring into all the minuteſt concernes thereof; and having made ſo great an Alliance betwixt his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Son, and a Princeſs of the
<hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> Houſe, his chief care is to heap up Treaſure ſufficient for the maintenance of ſo Illuſtrious Perſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:55404:31"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict Of the DUKE.</head>
               <p>HE is a young Prince not at all wanting of that Courage and Spirit of his Anceſtors; he is Prompt and Active, and keeps an abſolute Authority over all thoſe that are ſubmitted to him: yet hath he Allay enough to temper his heat, and do all things with prudence and circumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. He delights much in hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, even to the diſcompoſing himſelf ſometimes, as he did at <hi>Fountainbleau.</hi> He hath been a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55404:32"/>hard Student, and ſpeaks divers Languages. He hates great Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, and tedious Diſcourſes; and gives quick diſpatch to thoſe that addreſs themſelves to him about buſineſs. He promiſes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much for the future, and hath both Heart and Capacity enough to imitate his Fathers exploits of Warre.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid that he hath ſome hopes and pretences to the Crown of <hi>Poland.</hi> Certain it is, that he is the adopted Son of the King and Queen of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as having eſpouſed that Queens Niece. He does every thing very gracefully, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any affectation. He takes the upper hand of his Father, for what reaſon I know not, though ſome attribute it to a paternal Humility and Goodneſs, which I moſt encline to; as others ſay
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:55404:32"/>that it ariſes from the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Nobility, which aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the more, by how much it is the older and more diſtant from its Origine: others imagine it is only for his Fathers convenience, who thinks that place in the Coach leſs eaſie, holding this Maxime, <hi>That it is the Perſon gives the Dignity to the Place, not the Place to the Perſon;</hi> as may be obſerved in the Queen-Mother, who ever rides in the fore-part of the Coach. His knowledge is great in Poetry, he taking a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to read and remember things that are exquiſite in that kind. Every ordinary divertiſement does not reliſh with him, but there muſt be ſomething more then common in them to gaine his approbation. He anſwers any Philoſophical Queſtion with a great deal of Wit and Judgment;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:55404:33"/>and would pleaſe himſelf very much with a Magnificent Train, ſtately Balls and Maſques, and all other ſplendid appearances, if his Father did not moderate his inclinations a little, and reform his expences to the juſt meaſure of Decency, and the quality of his Illuſtrious Birth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:55404:33"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict OF THE Prince of
<hi>CONTY.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE is mild, good natur'd, and accompliſhed in all excellent Qualities. He is very Learned in all the Sciences, and hath been admired in the moſt celebrated Academy for his great Wit, and capacity in the knowledge of the higheſt points of <hi>Theology:</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his Titles and excellent Qualities, he is Maſter of a very great ſtock of Bounty and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. His life is a fit Exemplar for the beſt Courts, and makes
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:55404:34"/>good the poſſibility of being a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great Lord, and a very honeſt man.</p>
               <p>His Lady is a moſt vertuous Princeſs, who agrees admirably well with him in his Zeal and Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and had the Cardinal brought no other benefit to <hi>France,</hi> but the beſtowing of ſo rare a perſon on us, who is ſo Noble and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable to the World, he would deſerve our eternal thanks and praiſes, ſince by her means, Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of our lives have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved during the Famine; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the many Souls ſhe hath ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by her frequent Prayers and eminent Examples; inſomuch, as this Prince and Princeſs are the true patterns of Piety, amidſt the Pomp and Bravery of this Age. I ſhall not mention the Beauty of this Woman; for though ſhe be of an excelling Shape, yet that is the <pb n="57" facs="tcp:55404:34"/>leaſt of her perfections, ſhe being infinitely good and wiſe, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and diſcreet, and in a word, a complete Model of Chriſtian Perfection. There is a worthy Branch of the Noble Stock, who is called <hi>Monſieur le Comte,</hi> who is as yet too young to ſhew the World the advantages he is like to derive from ſuch a worthy Birth. All that is yet obſerved, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his raviſhing prettineſs, and ſuch a Phyſiognomy as promiſes he will hereafter keep up the Fame and Reputation of his Illuſtrious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="Anne Marie Louise d'Orléans, duchesse de Montpensier"
                 type="character">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:55404:35"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict Of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Montpenſier.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAdemoiſelle de Montpenſier</hi> the elder is of the houſe <hi>Bourbon,</hi> both by Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Gaſton</hi> the Son of <hi>France,</hi> yonger brother to <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIII, was her Father; and <hi>Mary de Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſier,</hi> his firſt wife, derived her Birth from
<hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſier;</hi> and that <hi>Henry</hi> from a third Son of the houſe of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> whoſe direct line failed at the death of the Conſtable, &amp; revived again in <hi>Charles</hi> the Second Son <pb n="59" facs="tcp:55404:35"/>of that Family: the third Son having begotten the Prince <hi>de la Roche, Suryon,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Montpenſier,</hi> from whom <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of <hi>Mademoiſelle</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended. The Princeſs being of the blood of Kings and Princes, is haughty, daring, and of a more then feminine courage. It may be truely ſaid, ſhe is an Amazon, and fitter to manage the Sword then a Diſtaff, which ſhe made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent at the buſineſs of St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonies,</hi> where the Princes fortunes being deſperate, and her Father not daring to appear, to ſave the Prince of
<hi>Conde</hi>'s party, who were at the brink of deſtruction; She went to the Town-hall, and took the Provoſt of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and the Governor of
<hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> by the Beards, uſing great threats, to oblige them to arm and raiſe the Citizens for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence <pb n="60" facs="tcp:55404:36"/>of the Prince; from whence ſhe went to her Father, his Royal Highneſs, in his Palace, whom ſhe in a manner conſtrained to go with her to the <hi>Baſtille,</hi> that ſo his preſence might ſupport the ſtaggering forces: and all that riſing of the Citizens, (an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize too rugged and daring for that foſter Sex, eſpecially againſt a Royal Army, and in preſence of their Majeſties) was an action hardly to be excuſed, but upon the conſideration of the raſhneſs of a woman, the Kings minority, and the general averſion at that time againſt Cardinal <hi>Mazarine.</hi> For ſhe commanded them to fire their Cannon upon the Kings Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and facilitated the Princes retreat, opening the City-Gates to him; which ſaved both him and his whole party from evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ruine. She is paſſionate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute <pb n="61" facs="tcp:55404:36"/>and active, free in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and endures not to be contradicted in her opinions. She never cared for the Kings, nor her Fathers Minſters, becauſe that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged her to ſome condeſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards them. She had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſome thoughts of marrying the Arch-Duke <hi>Leopold</hi> of
<hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria</hi> without the Kings conſent, which obliged his Majeſty to have a Guard attending her, and to ſecure all the paſſages into
<hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> leſt ſhe ſhould throw her ſelf into his Arms, who then made War againſt <hi>France.</hi> It is ſaid ſhe otherwhile refuſed the King of <hi>Englands</hi> courtſhip, during his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes; which is a fault of youth, not to be repaired. I hold it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what difficult to believe that her great heart could ſubmit it ſelf to any mans commands, how po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and noble ſoever he might <pb n="62" facs="tcp:55404:37"/>be. She is the richeſt Princeſs in <hi>Europe:</hi> for ſhe enjoys above eight hundred thouſand Livres revenue in Lands yearly. She is of a very tall and handſome proportion, of a Maſculine aſpect, a confident and free garb and pace, a majeſtick preſence, and yet a pleaſing and graceful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. Her humour is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what impatient, ſprightly, and forward to undertake whatever ſhe deſigns; and being a ſtranger to any kind of diſſimulation, ſpeaking her minde freely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſguiſe, not caring who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens. It is thought they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended at Court, that ſhe would expreſs ſome diſcontent, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Marriage of her youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Siſters before her, who were by another Mother; or elſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome reſentment written or ſpoken, ſhe was commanded to <pb n="63" facs="tcp:55404:37"/>withdraw her ſelf from the Court to her own Eſtate, where ſhe remains in a great deal of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and liberty, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much hopes of being ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly recalled to Court, where ſome advantagious propoſitions are on foot for a fit match for her, but with what Monarch is not ſo well known.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:55404:38"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict Of the Houſe of
<hi>Vendoſme.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Duke of <hi>Vendoſme,</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Caeſar</hi> of
<hi>Bourbon,</hi> is the natural Son of <hi>Henry</hi> the IV, and the Marchioneſs of <hi>Eſtree,</hi> called the beauteous <hi>Gabriele.</hi> The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive tenderneſs which the King his Father had for this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and for this Son, had almoſt cauſed his legitimation by a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, which the King had given his promiſe for, in favour of that Miſtreſs; which promiſe in writing <hi>Monſieur de Roſny</hi> tore in pieces
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:55404:38"/>in her preſence, as <hi>Monſieur de Sully</hi> mentions in his Memoires. He does very much reſemble that great Prince his Father; is well ſhaped, and of a good meen. He is ſomething jovial, and hath wit enough; but above theſe, he is really good natured, mild, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary affable. He was a long while abſent from Court with his Family, in the late Kings days; but ſince this Mans Reign, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned again with all the honour due to his birth and quality; nay, his Majeſty conferred the office of high Admiral upon him, which is one of the higheſt in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and hath beſtowed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion upon <hi>Monſieur de Beaufort</hi> the youngeſt of his Sons, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he is now higher at Court then ever; his age and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience making him capable of that great imployment, which he
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:55404:39"/>executes with all the conduct and advantage required, eſpecially by the aſſiſtance and activity of his Son. The Duke of
<hi>Mercoeur</hi> is his eldeſt Son, who marryed one of Cardinal
<hi>Mazarines</hi> Neeces: which match was kept ſecret; but in fine, ſhe being great with Child, they were compelled to a diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: there had been ſome propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions for this alliance before, which the Prince ſeemed to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from, for the intereſt of the Family; but the riddle being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd, there was no more with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it: the Cardinal having plaid the ſurer Game, fearing ſome oppoſition might ariſe. This Prince is very free and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, facile, and one that loves his divertiſements; he minds not much the Court-intrigues, but being Governour of <hi>Provence,</hi> he paſſes his time very contented<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <pb n="67" facs="tcp:55404:39"/>without that noiſe or magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence natural to his Family. The Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi> is a mild hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prince, and civil even beneath his quality. He was in raillery called <hi>Roy des Halles</hi> during the troubles, becauſe he was beloved and followed by all the populace, to whom he never refuſed to pull off his Hat. He is accompliſh'd and well proportioned, very fair, and rides a Horſe excellently; they ſay he is the beſt Marks-man with a Piſtol in
<hi>France.</hi> He had a ſad occaſion to try his skill, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſight at St. <hi>Anthonies,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Perſon of Mr. <hi>de Nemours</hi> his Brother-in-law, whom he kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the place, though againſt his will and inclination, which tends another way: ſome youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful raſhneſs precipitated <hi>Monſieur de Nemours</hi> to that duel, where
<hi>Beaufort</hi> was engaged of neceſſity <pb n="68" facs="tcp:55404:40"/>to defend himſelf: after the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy ſhot, he betook himſelf to the Convent of the
<hi>Chartreux</hi> with an inexpreſſible grief. The ſurvivance of the Admiralty is beſtowed upon him, in which quality he commands his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Fleet at Sea, againſt the <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bary</hi> Pirates of <hi>Tunis</hi> and
<hi>Algier.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:55404:40"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict Of the Duke of
<hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ISE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are none I ſuppoſe that are ignorant of the grandeur of this family under the laſt reigns, their elevation under <hi>Henry</hi> the II, their increaſe under <hi>Charles</hi> the IX; to whom they became jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, as well for the good meen, as their Magnificence; and in fine, their prodigious authority under <hi>Henry</hi> the III, who was obliged, for the ſecurity of his Crown, to ſecure the head of this Family at
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:55404:41"/>
                  <hi>Blois,</hi> together with his Brother the Cardinal. The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> his Son was propounded to be King of <hi>France</hi> by the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> during the League againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the IV, after his eſcape out of the Caſtle of <hi>Tours</hi> where the King held him priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>But the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi> looking upon him as a younger Brother of his Family, would not endure the propoſition, ins;o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as their diviſion ſerved to the advancement of the Kings af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, who pardoned him for that rebellion, according to his uſual clemency, and advanced, him to the Govenament of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur de Guiſe</hi> is at preſent the onely remaining branch of that Family; he retains very many of his Anceſtors worthy qualities, <pb n="71" facs="tcp:55404:41"/>and eſpecially their Magnificence, which is as it were natural to him. He is one of the greateſt Gallants in the Court, and in his youthful days was very amorous; he loved the Princeſs of
<hi>Nevers,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Polands</hi> Siſter, with a moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent paſſion. He married the Counteſs of <hi>Boſſum,</hi> one of the beautifulleſt Ladies of <hi>Flanders;</hi> and being afterwards paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enamoured with <hi>Madame du Pont,</hi> he went to
<hi>Rome</hi> to annul his firſt Marriage, that he might tye a new knot with this laſt. She kept an abſolute correſpondence with him, ſo that her love to him was as great as his to her. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unable to obtain his deſires of the Pope, he took occaſion to go to <hi>Naples,</hi> where all was in confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by reaſon of <hi>Thomas Anielo's</hi> revolt: At his arrival he became very conſiderable amongſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <pb n="72" facs="tcp:55404:42"/>of that great City; and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering himſelf with the hopes of making a Conqueſt of it for the King, provided they would ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour him from
<hi>France,</hi> he added in his Letter, written to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>That he deſired no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence for that glorious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, but onely to have</hi> Madam du Pont. Whereupon the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal judging this paſſion and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion a ſign of weakneſs in him; and being unwilling to hazard ſo many men upon ſo vain an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, left him to himſelf; ſo that being taken Priſoner by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and carried into their Country, he was freed again du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the troubles in <hi>Guienne,</hi> at the Requeſt of the Prince, thinking thereby to gain him to his own party; but the King having diſpatched <hi>Monſieur de Verderonne</hi> to releaſe him, he
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:55404:42"/>came directly to Court, without ſo much as once waiting on the Prince, to whom he was obliged for moving the buſineſs firſt; which occaſioned the Court to take ſome notice of it, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards obtain his liberty. Since that time he hath ſold and waſted moſt of his eſtate upon a new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign on <hi>Naples,</hi> and the <hi>Idea's</hi> of conquering a Kingom. Without doubt he hath a great ſoul; but being unlimited, he hath waſted the Eſtate of the whole Family: whereupon <hi>Madam de Guiſe</hi> (ſpeaking once to the Queen-Mother) ſaid, <hi>That the Dukes of</hi> Guiſe <hi>had formerly amaſſed ſo much Riches, that they were become jealous and terrible, but there was now an Heir able to destroy and ſquander all away again, ſo that there would be no cauſe of fear and apprehenſion of their great <pb n="74" facs="tcp:55404:43"/>neſs hereafter.</hi> He is well ſhap'd, obliging, mild, civil, amorous; he ſpeaks exactly, and writes good verſe, having ſome knowledge of whatever is exquiſite. He hath as it were, a natural faculty in riding and managing a great Horſe, and behaves himſelf more gracefully then any man at the running at the Ring, or any kind of Turnament. He is infinitely delighted with thoſe noble exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, which he undertakes with more happineſs then any Querry in <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are likewiſe in <hi>France</hi> ſome younger Brothers of the Houſe of <hi>Lorraine;</hi> amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the Count of
<hi>Harcourt,</hi> frank, haughty, valiant, as he hath ſhewed himſelf in ſeveral oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, eſpecially before <hi>Turin</hi> againſt the Marquis <hi>D'Eguux,</hi> who had invited the Ladies of <pb n="75" facs="tcp:55404:43"/>that City to ſee him make a breakfaſt of the French, where himſelf was ſoundly beaten by this Count of <hi>Harcourt,</hi> who had not above ſeven thouſand men againſt fifteen thouſand. He al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo performed ſome things that ſeem to be above all belief at the taking the Iſſes of St. <hi>Marguerit,</hi> and St. <hi>Honorat,</hi> with a very ſmall force, contrary to the Worlds expectation.</p>
               <p>He made War likewiſe in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> but not ſo ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, being forced in his Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches before <hi>Lerida.</hi> He under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took, and effected above hopes, the conducting of the Princes of the blood, <hi>Conde, Conty</hi> and <hi>Longueville,</hi> Priſoners to <hi>Havre de Grace.</hi> He hath the Office of Grand <hi>Eſcuyer</hi> of
<hi>France,</hi> and the Count of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magnac</hi> his Son hath the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion <pb n="76" facs="tcp:55404:44"/>verſion; and it is ſaid, old and tyred as he is, he yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires the King would imploy him in his ſervice, that he may dye no otherwhere but in the Field, the Bed of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:55404:44"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict Of the Houſe of
<hi>Longueville.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Count <hi>De St. Paul</hi> ought to have been ranged before the Duke of <hi>Guiſe;</hi> but becauſe of the Kings Declaration in favor of the Houſe of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> that they ſhall go next to the Princes of the Blood of <hi>France,</hi> I obſerve that Method, though it be yet but in
<hi>Idea,</hi> and againſt which, this Prince hath made his Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which for my part I ſhall not intereſt my ſelf in, but leave it wholly to his Majeſties deciſion. <pb n="78" facs="tcp:55404:45"/>And truly his Family, although deſcended from <hi>John Count de Dunois,</hi> a natural Son of the Duke of
<hi>Orleans,</hi> hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared capable of ſucceeding to the Crown, having aſſiſted the <hi>Pucelle</hi> of <hi>Orleans</hi> more then any one in regaining the Kingdome from the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who had uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped it in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the VII. He is the Son of <hi>Henry</hi> of
<hi>Orleans</hi> lately deceaſed, who hath left him Heir of much Wealth, and more Vertues; he being a Prince of the greateſt hopes in the World. He is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry graceful Perſon, of much Wit, Courage and Learning; a great lover of Arts and Sciences, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and in ſine, one that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to be nothing leſs then his great Anceſtor, who rendred this Kingdom ſuch eminent and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ſervices. But he is yet <pb n="79" facs="tcp:55404:45"/>only learning his Exerciſes, which he begins to perform with that dexterity, that the world ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires him. His eldeſt Brother is become a Jeſuite, and hath left him ſole Heir of the richeſt Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amongſt the Princes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:55404:46"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict OF THE New Houſe of
<hi>Soiſſons.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE who at preſent bears the Title of the Count of
<hi>Soiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> is the youngeſt Son of the decaſed Prince
<hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the Princeſs of <hi>Carignan,</hi> Daughter of the true Houſe of <hi>Soiſſons.</hi> He is well ſhap'd, mild, and civil; and is, as it were, the eldeſt of the Family, his eldeſt Brother being both deaf and dumb. He married one of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<hi>Mazarines</hi> Nieces, by which means he got very much in favor.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:55404:46"/>He enjoys the Command of Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel of the
<hi>Swiſſers,</hi> which is one of the handſomeſt imployments about the Court. Beſides this, he is Governour of <hi>Champagne</hi> and <hi>Brie,</hi> and in a word, is one of the beſt ſetled Princes in the whole Kingdom. He was in diſgrace ſome years ſince for attempting to draw his Sword upon the Duke of <hi>Novailles,</hi> in behalf of his Wife, who contended with the Dukes Lady about the Priviledge of giving the Queen her Napkin; but he is now reſtored again, and more then ever reſpected by his Majeſty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:55404:47"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict Of the Houſe of
<hi>Courtenay.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Family, though very il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious, and indeed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> is very low at preſent; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the King out of his meet bounty be pleaſed to raiſe them again, they muſt be contented to remain as they are, the Relicks of a Princely Houſe, with onely the bare title of Nobility.</p>
               <p>There are yet extant of this Family a Father and Son, called Princes of <hi>Courtenay;</hi> and a Knight <pb n="83" facs="tcp:55404:47"/>of
<hi>Malta,</hi> a younger Sprigg of them. Nothing is more true, then that they were of the Royal ſtock, having loſt their right of Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by their own default and negligence, having miſ-allied themſelves, and changed their Coat of the Arms of <hi>France,</hi> which they ſhould ever have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, as an infallible mark of their Original. Thus have they deprived themſelves voluntarily of a great advantage; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Law,
<q>Volenti non ſit Injuria.</q>
               </p>
               <p>They remain ſtill in obſcurity, though they have many times en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to raiſe themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and reſtore their Family to its wonted quality and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour.</p>
               <p>There are other Lords who <pb n="84" facs="tcp:55404:48"/>take upon them the title of Princes, as the Princes of <hi>Bouillon,</hi> or <hi>Sedan, De la Rochefaucalt, De Marſillac, De Tarante;</hi> amongſt whom, the moſt conſiderable for his great exploits, is the Marſhal <hi>Turenne,</hi> younger Son of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Bouillon.</hi> He is a perſon of great conduct, and admirable judgement; prudent in the midſt of Battles, and fearleſs in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and perils: and though he hath not always had the ſucceſs he deſerved; yet in the opinion of brave Warriours, he is eſteemed one of the greateſt Captains this Age affords. He was ever moſt fortunate when he commanded for the King, as may be obſerved by the taking of
<hi>Stenay,</hi> his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving of <hi>Arras,</hi> and the gaining of the moſt important places in <hi>Flanders,</hi> before the concluſion of the laſt peace: On the contrary, <pb n="85" facs="tcp:55404:48"/>at the Battle of
<hi>Rhetel,</hi> he loſt a great number of men, and had like to have been taken Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner himſelf. He married the Daughter of the deceaſed Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal <hi>de la Force,</hi> by whom he hath no Iſſue. He hath no defect, but that of his Religion, founded upon a falſe Maxime, <hi>That a man ought to dye in that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion he was born in;</hi> which ought not to be maintained, but in the true Church. He is a man of Faith, and of his word, in reſpect of the world; and glories in this, that he never failed of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to any one; which begets a great deal of credit and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance towards him.</p>
               <p>There is likewiſe the Marſhal <hi>Gramond,</hi> Soveraign of
<hi>Bidache,</hi> who is one of the ableſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours about the Court, and one that wants not for any cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage <pb n="86" facs="tcp:55404:49"/>at a time of need. He o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beys Authority and Command as it were blindfold, and is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed for giving Battle at <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nincourt</hi> againſt all appearance of ſucceſs: but when this raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was objected againſt him, he anſwered, That he had a writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Order from the Cardinal <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelieu,</hi> who then had the ſole command; and this was when the King was at <hi>Perpignan,</hi> and the Cardinal, as it were, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace; who to re-eſtabliſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his former power, and get an opportunity to revenge himſelf of thoſe Enemies that had brought him to that condition, by the means of his Royal Highneſs, and <hi>monſieur de</hi> St. <hi>Mare,</hi> he deſigned to give the King this conſiderable Chocque, being then at a great diſtance from
<hi>Paris</hi> and the Frontiers of <hi>Flanders;</hi> 
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:55404:49"/>which ſucceeded juſt as he deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it: for the King being ſurprized at this ſudden blow, and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all was loſt, ſaid aloud,
<hi>Alas! then ſhall I not return to</hi> Paris! for they had apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for that great City, deſtitute of any Forces, and too far from any relief againſt a victorious Army. But <hi>Monſieur de Noyers</hi> taking his time, replyed, <hi>Sir, there is none but the Cardinal that can ward this fatal blow.</hi> Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the King immediately ſent for him, and reſtored all power and commands to him, enjoyning him to provide for the ſafety of the Nation, and take a juſt revenge of his oppoſers, who were imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſeized, and <hi>Monſieur de</hi> St. <hi>Mare</hi> and
<hi>Monſieur de Thou</hi> exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted at <hi>Lyons</hi> a while after, as guilty of Treaſon againſt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, in the perſon of his chief Miniſter of State.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="Jean François Paul de Gondi, cardinal de Retz" type="character">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:55404:50"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict OF THE Cardinal <hi>de Retz.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Cardinal is the Son of the General of the Gallies, by name Father <hi>Gondy,</hi> Prieſt of the <hi>Oratory.</hi> And the reaſon which moved him to take a Religious Habit was this; having informed the King of ſomewhat, he quoted <hi>Monſieur de Liancourt</hi> for his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor: the King having ſent for <hi>Monſieur de Liancourt</hi> to know the truth, he flatly denied that he had mentioned any ſuch thing to <hi>Monſieur de Gondy.</hi> This affront <pb n="89" facs="tcp:55404:50"/>of giving him the lye, ſhould have ſucceeded to a Duel; but reſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his reſentment and ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to God in favour of his friend, he reſolved to quit the Court, and indeed the World, and retire himſelf to thoſe Fathers of the
<hi>Oratory.</hi> His Son at that time Abbot of St. <hi>Berigre</hi> was elected Coadjutor to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> his Uncle. During the Troubles, he made himſelf fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous under that quality, having raiſed a Regiment for the <hi>Pariſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> which at Court was in a ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing way called the <hi>Corinthian Band,</hi> from his being entituled to that Arch-Biſhoprick of <hi>Corinth, In partibus inſidelium.</hi> He obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Court to make him a Cardinal, even againſt their Wills; for the Cardinal
<hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> being otherwiſe unable to break that Party called <hi>Les Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deurs,</hi> 
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:55404:51"/>whereof he was Chief, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to fruſtrate him of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals Cap, and deluded him; and therefore upon their diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that League framed againſt him, he had the grant of the Kings nomination of him for a <hi>Cardinal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> but another Expreſs was immediately diſpatched after his Meſſenger, to oppoſe his Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at <hi>Rome,</hi> which he ſomewhat doubted of; and having given his Kinſman, the <hi>Bailly Gondy,</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of State to the Great Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> notice of it, he ſet all his Friends, and all the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines imaginable on work to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his Family by this means; and having at the ſame time cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Mazarines</hi> Meſſenger to be way-laid in his paſſage, he was ſtopp'd while they carried on their deſign at
<hi>Rome,</hi> where they obliged the Pope to call an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:55404:51"/>Aſſembly, to expedite the buſineſs: So that having elu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Cardinals crafty deſign by this handſome ſubtilty, he grew very much fuſpected at Court, where they believed him capable of great undertakings. Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> became both jealous and afraid of him, and therefore to enſnare him, he was flattered with the hopes of being made a Miniſter of State, to which the Queen-Mother ſeemed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline. This extraordinary favour having ſwell'd his thoughts, he imagined he might attain it, and went to Court, accompanied with his Guards, attending the Queen with great exactneſs. In the end, ſtaying there one day at Dinner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, the Queen bid him go to dinner himſelf; but he waiting till the Queens Fruit was ſerved in, and then taking his leave with <pb n="92" facs="tcp:55404:52"/>great reſpect, and having had ſome good words from her Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, he was ſeized on upon the Stair by a Captain of the Guards, who commanded him in the Kings name, to go into a Room, where they had a Dinner provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for him; after which he was carried to <hi>Vincennes,</hi> and there tranſported to
<hi>Nants</hi> Caſtle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing committed to the Cuſtody of the Marſhal
<hi>de Milleray.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He made his eſcape from that Priſon, and riding poſt to ſave himſelf, fell, and put his Arm out of joynt. There were ſome ſent after him; but having cauſed ſome of his Gentlemen to continue riding in the ordinary Road, he deceived thoſe that purſued him, and kept himſelf concealed in a Barn, which he afterwards for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook, and travelled in By-ways. He went out of the Kingdom the <pb n="93" facs="tcp:55404:52"/>neereſt way, and retired himſelf in St. <hi>Sebaſtians</hi> Port, which is under the
<hi>Spaniards</hi> Dominion.</p>
               <p>The Governour having heard of his arrival, ſent notice to the King his Maſter; and according to Order, came and viſited the Cardinal
<hi>de Retz,</hi> and offered him 7000 Piſtols. The Cardinal refuſed them, telling him, he would receive money from none but the King his own Maſter; and all he craved of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> was a free paſſage, and ſecurity againſt his Enemies, which he hoped for. The Governour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, That the King of <hi>Spain</hi> was able enough to make ſuch preſents, and did not pretend thereby to gain a perſon of his quality to ſide with him, but he intreated him not to refuſe that liberality. The Cardinal being fully reſolved not to accept of <pb n="94" facs="tcp:55404:53"/>any thing, though he were in the extremeſt neceſſity: The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour returned next day with 2000 onely, and told him, That the King of <hi>Spain</hi> knew he was in want of ſome money, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would take it very kindly if he accepted but of that ſmall ſum: Whereupon the Cardinal being unwilling to ſhew too much obſtinacy, took 500 to ſerve him only for defraying his charges in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to:
<hi>Toſcany,</hi> whither he deſigned to go; and returning his thanks to the King by the Governour, he proſecuted his journey the very next day. He arrived at <hi>Florence,</hi> where he was very cordially re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and treated with all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable magnificence: amongſt other rarities which were ſhewed him at the Great Dukes Palace, he ſtood a while to gaze on the Picture of <hi>John de Medicis,</hi> a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, <pb n="95" facs="tcp:55404:53"/>and General of an Army, in a negligent habit, as it was ſaid, he was wont to go; whereupon he ſaid, <hi>Thoſe Gentlemen our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors were not ſo Ceremonious as we are now adays; and yet I believe they were no leſs honeſt and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable then we are now.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But though he had boaſted then, that in deſpite of Cardinal
<hi>Mazarine,</hi> he ſhould die Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Paris;</hi> yet he hath ſhewed a great deal of modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his ſurrender of it into the hands of his Majeſty, who made it known that ſuch was his Royal pleaſure.</p>
               <p>He is, without doubt, very ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous, magnificent, and full of honour and vertue; learned, wiſe, and very capable of being a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of State, were he called to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:55404:54"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict of Cardinal <hi>Baberino,</hi> Called the Cardinal <hi>Antonio.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE is Nephew of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the VIII, and the youngeſt Son of his Family. He is great Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain of the holy Church (Chair) and in his Name are all affairs diſpatched after the death of the Pope, and during the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, in whoſe life-time he keeps his Holineſſes Ring. He is
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:55404:54"/>great Almoner of <hi>France,</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of
<hi>Rheims,</hi> firſt Duke and Pair of <hi>France,</hi> Abbot of <hi>S. Denis.</hi> He was born Commander of the Kings Orders, and hath the right of Information touching the lives and behaviours of the Knights of the Order, and receives the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their faith. This Office is <hi>Solstitium Honorum</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> the Zenith of all Honours; which was created by <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt, in favour of Cardinal <hi>Antonio Menden.</hi> He adminiſters the Oath of Fidelity to the King, and takes it of all the other Eccleſiaſticks, according to the Court of Biſhops and Archbiſhops of <hi>France,</hi> Grand Priors of <hi>Aquitaine, Auvergne, Champagne,</hi> and other conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Abbies. He delivers the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners from their bondage upon ſolemn Feſtivals, or days of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation, and the like extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <pb n="98" facs="tcp:55404:55"/>occaſions. He diſpoſes of the whole ſtock of the Kings Alms, and exerciſes all theſe Functions, without any dependence upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as ſuperiour; which power he can communicate to whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he pleaſeth. He is milde, peaceable and humble; loves the French way of living, and hath otherwhile governed the affairs of the Church during the life of his Uncle. It is reported of him, that when the War hapned to be made upon the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> having no great skill in the Military Art, he ſtudied a whole night to frame an equivocal Letter when he was to ſend his Orders to the Generals; that ſo, in caſe things ſucceeded wel, he might reap the glory of the Enterpriſe; and if Fortune were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, there might be room enough left to excuſe himſelf, by preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they had not comprehended his meaning in their attempts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:55404:55"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict OF The Chancellour.</head>
               <p>MOnſieur <hi>Seguier,</hi> iſſued from a family of the Robe, hath had ſome of his anceſtors officia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the greateſt State-employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Such men are uſually made to paſs thorow thoſe lower employments of the Long Robe firſt, and are afterwards according to their abilities called up to the Soveraign degree of Chancellour of <hi>France,</hi> which is the chief of all Judicature. He is prudent <pb n="100" facs="tcp:55404:56"/>and judicious, and is accounted the moſt learned perſon in the Kingdom. He declares his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties minde when he liſts in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; who having in few words expreſſed himſelf, to take off the trouble of a long
<hi>Harangue,</hi> tells them, <hi>My Chancellour ſhall inform of what I have more to ſay.</hi> He ſits at the Kings feet on a black Velvet Cuſhion; preſiding in the Great Council in his Majeſties abſence; which Office he holds for his whole life. The Seals may be ſometimes indeed taken from him, and committed to ſuch a Keeper as the King ſhall make choice of, to ſeal Orders that are paſſed. Though he perfectly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted himſelf to the Kings will in all things, yet was the Seal gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from him to the firſt Preſident <hi>Monſieur Molet,</hi> during the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of <hi>Paris,</hi> he being purſued <pb n="101" facs="tcp:55404:56"/>by the raſcally people to the
<hi>Hoſtel de Luynes,</hi> whither he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to retreat, and in much dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger even there of being forced out, had not the Marſhal <hi>de la Milleray</hi> come and reſcued him by force of arms. The fear and jealouſie he had of <hi>Monſieur Fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet</hi> at <hi>Fountainbleau,</hi> made him follow the King every where: and he ſhewed himſelf as able and active as any young man in the Journey to <hi>Britany,</hi> becauſe he had heard, as it is reported, that the King ſhould ſay to <hi>Monſieur Fouquet,</hi> who importuned him to take the Seals from him, ſeeing his very great age diſabled him in the execution of that Office; <hi>Do not trouble your ſelf; aſſoon as I return from Britany, I aſſure you the Seals ſhall be in your houſe:</hi> which was true indeed, all things being ſealed there.
<hi>Monſieur Fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet</hi> 
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:55404:57"/>making a favourable, though not a right conſtruction of that promiſe, was ſatisfied therewith; and the Chancellor had a great apprehenſion, endeavouring by his cloſe attendance to make it appear to his Majeſtic, that he had yet vigour enough left him to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit himſelf of that truſt. This is one of the cauſes of the enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty betwixt him and <hi>Monſieur Fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He cheriſhes his wealth above all the things in the world, and is ſparing for nothing that may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to prolong his days, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king frequent uſe of Cordials, and excellent nouriſhment; which have been ſo effectual, that he is in a perfect condition of health at the age of Fourſcore years. He hath always a Guard with him when he goes abroad; which is rather for a mark of his dignity, <pb n="103" facs="tcp:55404:57"/>then for fear of any hurt or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. He preſides in the Court of Juſtice; but <hi>Monſieur Fouquet</hi> hath put in many Heads of Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation againſt him, by no means accepting or owning him for his Judge. He is prodigiouſly rich, and very oeconomical; and having no male-iſſue, his Succeſſion is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved to his daughters husbands, the chief whereof is the Marquis <hi>de Coaſlin.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:55404:58"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict Of <hi>Monſieur Colbert.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE is the ſon of an eminent Citizen of <hi>Rheims:</hi> but thoſe who are very well vers'd in Genealogies, affirm that he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from one of the moſt Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Families of <hi>Scotland.</hi> He was firſt under <hi>Monſieur Tellier</hi> the Secretary of State; and when the Cardinal was exiled from the Court, and retired into <hi>Germany,</hi> having enquired of <hi>Monſieur Tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi> for ſome perſon whom he might conſide in, to intruſt with <pb n="105" facs="tcp:55404:58"/>ſome Jewels of a very great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, and certain ſums of money; <hi>Monſieur Tellier</hi> named
<hi>Monſieur Colbert</hi> to him, as a very honeſt confiding man, whoſe fidelity he was well acquainted with; who having a houſe at <hi>Rheims</hi> juſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Road betwixt <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Cologne,</hi> the Cardinal left in his keeping the moſt conſiderable treaſure he had, which he laid up for his laſt reſerve, and found this the moſt convenient place that could be to diſpoſe of it as occaſion might require. His E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence lodged two nights at his houſe, and appointed him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and convey all his Letters of Correſpondence which he either d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpatched to, or received from the Court; which Commerce he was the fitter to drive, being then not generally known; of which he acquitted himſelf with ſo <pb n="106" facs="tcp:55404:59"/>much exactneſs, integrity, and ſucceſs, that he deſerved to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with matters of more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance: and indeed, from that time he grew much in favour with the Cardinal, who being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called into <hi>France,</hi> and happily reſetled at Court, deſired to have him from <hi>Monſieur Tellier,</hi> and made him Intendant of his houſe, which he governed till his death to the great liking of that grand Miniſter; inſomuch as the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal upon his death-bed, and in his Will and Teſtament, whereof he was Executor, recommended him particularly to the King, intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Majeſtie to make uſe of him as a perſon of a tried Ability and Faith.</p>
               <p>The King hath found him ſuch a one indeed, according to his own deſire, and the fitteſt man in the whole Nation to manage his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury; <pb n="107" facs="tcp:55404:59"/>and therefore having ſet aſide
<hi>Monſieur Fouquet,</hi> he gave the whole Adminiſtration and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of it to this perſon, whom he hath likewiſe honoured with the Office of Chief Survey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or of his Buildings and Royal Houſes; and, which is more, does not ſeldom communicate the weightieſt affairs of State unto him.</p>
               <p>He is indeclinably devoted to the will and ſervice of his Maſter. A perſon he is without any thing of vain-glory or boaſting, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in expences, who willingly ſacrifices all his pleaſures and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements to the intereſt of his Country and affairs of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. He is active and vigilant, conſtant and inviolable in any thing of his duty; avoiding all making of Parties and Cabals, not treating with any body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:55404:60"/>the Kings knowledge, or an expreſs Order from his Majeſtic. He ſeems not to thirſt after much riches for himſelf, but is hugely diligent and active in heaping up Treaſure for his Maſter, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Revenues of the Crown; and being well verſed in ordering thoſe things, he gives the King his beſt advice to redeem that part of his Demeſnes which hath been long engaged, thereby filling his Coffers, and increaſing his daily Income. By theſe pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent means he hath already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived many Millions, which were concealed, detained, and unjuſtly converted to other uſes, by ſuch as formerly had the management of the Treaſury; not fearing the ill will of any, to do his Maſter ſervice; relying wholly upon the juſtice and power of a Monarch able to protect him againſt all his adverſaries.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:55404:60"/>
               <p>It is reported, that he hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured his Majeſtie that in three years time he will redeem and clear all his Demeſnes; which when accompliſhed, will make him the richeſt Potentate of Chriſtendom, which he is indeed already, in the reputation of all ſtranger-Nations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:55404:61"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict OF <hi>Monſieur Tellier.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE is deſcended of a Family of the Long Robe; and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf to the height he is now at, as much by his own dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and conduct, as by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> who made him chief Maſter of Requeſts. He is of a friendly, diſcreet, and prudent temper, and one that underſtands Military af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs better then any man in the Kingdom; I mean, as to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how to keep up and maintain
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:55404:61"/>an Army, what the charge will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to according to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers raiſed, and the like: which knowledge he hath acquired by a very long experience. He hath maintained himſelf unblameable in his Office, and was but feigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſgraced or ſet aſide during the Inteſtine Troubles. For the Prince complaining that the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, though baniſhed, ſtill ruled at Court by means of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, amongſt whom
<hi>Monſieur Tellier</hi> &amp; <hi>Monſieur de Lionne</hi> were counted the principal; the Queen, to take away all cauſe of jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, cauſed them to be ſent out of <hi>Paris,</hi> and promiſed to admit no more of them to her Council: which Order within a month was again reverſed, and the policie of this Court-turn apparent. He is a perſon nothing tainted with the vanities of the times, having no <pb n="112" facs="tcp:55404:62"/>ambitious thoughts, but perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his duty meerly out of a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of honour and honeſty, not minding either concurrences nor enmities, not aiming at higher pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments or greater profits, being already in a condition, indeed, ſo good in theſe reſpects, that there is little left him to wiſh for.</p>
               <p>He hath a ſon, the Marquis <hi>de Louvais,</hi> very much in favour with the King, to whom his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie has granted the reverſion of his Fathers Office of Secretary of State for Military affairs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:55404:62"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict Of <hi>Monſieur de Lionne.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE is of a Noble Family, and was formerly chief Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Queen-mother; and when ſhe was Regent, he was em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in State-affairs; and the Cardinal, a while before his death, recommended him to his Majeſtie in particular, as a man fit for the employments he holds. He is one of the moſt prudent men in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope;</hi> one that hath the moſt flegme, and reſervedneſs of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as the Italians themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:55404:63"/>when he was amongſt them; they endeavoured by all the ways imaginable to make him diſcover himſelf, but with all their ſubtilty they could not make themſelves Maſters of the leaſt of his ſecrets.</p>
               <p>The Great Duke, and the whole Houſe of <hi>Medices</hi> treated him to that very end, and laid all the plots &amp; ſnares they could; but all their diligence and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning could not entice him to utter one ſillable but what was meerly indifferent. He went ſince joynt Ambaſſadour with the Marſhal <hi>de Gramont</hi> into <hi>Germany,</hi> at the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of the Emperour: and we may truly ſay, that the two ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilleſt and wiſeſt Politicians of <hi>France</hi> did then ſhare together in that Illuſtrious Negotiation. He is a perſon of much honeſty and conſcience, and one that will not <pb n="115" facs="tcp:55404:63"/>make uſe of any one that is not good and vertuous; though it were his misfortune a while ſince to have a perſon in his Family who was a Traytor both to him, the King, and the State: but this was a fellow taken in by his other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, not of his chuſing: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found that his Secrets were divulged to Forraign Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours by his infidelity, he cauſed him to be chaſtiſed according to his deſerts, having made him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that he had never ſpoken ſo much as one word to him. He is a lover of Vertue and Arts; is milde, affable, of a good preſence, and exactly faithful in the Kings concerns: and though he be Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of State for all Forraign affairs, which he underſtands in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably well, yet in the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals Will he is preferred before all others to inform the King of <pb n="116" facs="tcp:55404:64"/>all the concerns of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> and whatever is to be tranſacted with the Duke
<hi>Charles,</hi> who is one of the ſubtilleſt and wary Princes of this Age; of whom the Duke ſaid, <hi>that he was a fit man to be treated with, but it must be onely for three days.</hi> Which words he taking hold of, did indeed finiſh his Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion within that ſpace of time, as is apparent by the Treaty mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Signed to by each of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="Charles Louis Auguste Fouquet, duc de Belle-Isle" type="character">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:55404:64"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict OF <hi>Monſieur Foucquet.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE is the ſon of a Citizen, and pretends the original of his Family is Noble. He roſe to his Fortune by his Brother the Abbot
<hi>Foucquet</hi>'s means, who was much in favor with Cardinal
<hi>Mazarine.</hi> He borrowed a ſum of money to buy the Office of Attorney-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and in that quality did the Cardinal many good Offices in the Parliament, and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Paris.</hi> He was very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act in proſecuting any that wrote <pb n="118" facs="tcp:55404:65"/>againſt that Miniſter. Yet all theſe Services could not exempt him from being ſuſpected; which obliged him to draw up that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, found amongſt his rifled Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, to defend himſelf in caſe he were attaqu'd. The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals favour procured him the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of Superintendant, which he managed alone after the deceaſe of <hi>Monſieur Servien,</hi> who during a time ſhared it with him. He hath a vaſt and lofty ſpirit, and was the profuſeſt and moſt magnificent man in the Kingdom. His ambitious minde made him chuſe this Motto for his Deviſe:
<q>
                     <p>Quo non aſcendam?</p>
                     <p>Whither ſhall I not climb?</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And it is believed his thoughts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired at being Chief Miniſter: but the King by no means endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to have any Subject raiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <pb n="119" facs="tcp:55404:65"/>to that Authority in his Reign, reſerving that power moſt juſtly for himſelf, cauſed him to be arreſted ſome years ſince in his journey to <hi>Brittany,</hi> and ſent him to
<hi>Vincennes,</hi> and from thence to the <hi>Bastille.</hi> He was liberal with profuſion, being accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of having ſquandred away infinite ſums of money upon his Pleaſures and Miſtreſſes. He is likewiſe accuſed of allowing ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral large Penſions to the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees at Court, to be his creatures; it being his Opinion and Maxime, that no mans Faith could be of proof againſt Fifty thouſand Crowns. His Buildings do alſo ſhew his exceſſive Prodigality, together with the Furniture, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Attendance, Rarities, and unparallel'd Banquets; as for example, the Collation he gave his Majeſtie at <hi>Veau de Vicomte,</hi> 
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:55404:66"/>where he expended Fourty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crowns, by all computation. He beſtowed great Largeſſes like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe upon the Jeſuites, <hi>viz.</hi> a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary, a Thouſand livres of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Rent to maintain it, and Fourſcore thouſand livres for a Building within their Colledge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:55404:66"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict Of The Firſt Preſident of PARLIAMENT.</head>
               <p>MOnſieur <hi>de la Mignon</hi> (iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from a Family of the Long Robe) enjoys this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Office, which is onely at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto by Merit and Ability; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being never ſold, no more then the Chancellors place, as being not to be valued at its worth. He repreſents the Kings perſon in Parliament, and acknowledges no Superiour to him in the whole <pb n="122" facs="tcp:55404:67"/>Kingdom for Judicial matters, being Head of a Soveraign Court. He was a Fellow-Preſident long before he arrived to this chief di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity. He is eloquent without affectation, learned without am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and one of the wiſeſt heads of the Nation. He is an enemy to the <hi>Janſenists,</hi> and all other Novelties; being ſo much wedded to ancient Cuſtoms, that he will not admit of any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion either in Church, or Maxims of State or Law. He adheres moſt ſtrictly to the Royal Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and receives all Orders from his Majeſtie with a great deal of veneration, and zeal to put them in execution. They ſay he is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much Jeſuited, becauſe he is of their opinion concerning the Doctrine of the Times: never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs he ſhews a very even tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in all his actions, not refuſing <pb n="123" facs="tcp:55404:67"/>to hear any of the contrary party; judging with equity and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and doing juſtice where it is requiſite. He is a perſon of an excellent good nature, very cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, loving peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as well in State as Church. So that it may be truly ſaid of him, that he is the common Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to his Country, on whom he beſtows all his Cares and Labours, in rendering every one what is his due; being juſt and merciful to the good, and a puniſher of the wicked; which are the chief and onely Pillars of a State. So that the King hath reaſon to rely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him for that part of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which he adminiſters with an unbyaſſed integrity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="François Honorat de Beauvilliers, duc de Saint-Aignan"
                 type="character">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:55404:68"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict OF THE The Duke of <hi>S. Agnan.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE hath ſignalized himſelf in divers encounters for his Majeſties ſervice, and verified it in his own perſon, That true Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry does not debaſe a Coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious heart. The height of his Valour and Skill was manifeſted in an odde Adventure, which might have proved his utter ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, and the loſs of many a brave Courtier. Three men mounted to the beſt advantage, and having Vizards on, lay in Ambuſcado
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:55404:68"/>neer one of his Country-houſes, to ſurpriſe him unawares and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, intending to murther him, as they had done infallibly, if his great courage and reſolution had not carried him off that evident peril. The Story of it is ſo well known, that I thought it needleſs to inſert it here at length.</p>
               <p>He is the moſt obliging Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the world, from whom, I never heard any one ſay that he came diſſatisfied. No man loves Learning, or perſons of ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, more then himſelf: and ſo well verſed he is, that ſeveral ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry handſom Things have been compoſed by him; amongſt the which is a Comedy of his faſhion, made to divert the Court; and the Kings voyage to <hi>Bretagne;</hi> written in French in one nights time, at his Majeſties command. He is highly cheriſhed by the King <pb n="126" facs="tcp:55404:69"/>for his gallant wit, and generous inclinations. It is very fit, that ſo brave a man ſhould be in favour with ſo great a Monarch, whom he cannot but inſpire with noble and good Sentiments: for all he either ſaith or does is honeſt and worthy. Formerly the Titles of Minions and Favourites were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to ſuch perſons: at preſent, that of Conſident is more in vogue. But this Duke has no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quality, then what <hi>Ephestion</hi> had from <hi>Alexander;</hi> and it may be truly ſaid, that he entirely loves the perſon of the King, to whom he is a faithful Guardian, and a moſt zealous ſervant. He ſpeaks very well and gracefully; hath a wonderful preſence, and an unparallel'd ſweetneſs in conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; ſo that he may very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be eſteemed as a Model of a compleat Courtier, and a very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Gentleman.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="François de Créquy, marquis de Marines" type="character">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:55404:69"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict Of The Duke of
<hi>Crequi.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Lord was ſon of a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal of <hi>France,</hi> and is the chief Gentleman of the Kings Bedchamber; one of the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeſt, haughtieſt, and braveſt men of the whole Court. He is frank and liberal, and keeps up the Character of his ancient No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility. He neither is acquainted with diſſimulation, intrigues, or deſignes, but goes roundly to work, and maintains the Kings intereſt with heat, not fearing any <pb n="128" facs="tcp:55404:70"/>thing can be oppoſed. He is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the Camp then the Cabinet or Council, being as it were born to that Noble Exerciſe. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs he was ſent upon an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Embaſſie to <hi>Rome,</hi> to congratulate the Popes new Election, and complement him in his Maſters behalf; which was onely an act of Civility, the King not being at all obliged, like ſome other Princes, to pay this reſpect to the Holy Chair, but onely of his free-will: ſo that the Romanes and their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours did hugely miſtake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in forfeiting that reſpect due to the dignity of <hi>Monſieur de Crequi,</hi> and violating the right of Princes in his perſon, and the perſon of Madam the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drice. It muſt be noted here, that all Ambaſſadours wives in <hi>Italy</hi> take the ſame Title and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:55404:70"/>Quality as their Husbands, and as ſuch, take place accordingly in all Aſſemblies. But the Conteſt being fully compoſed, and ſatisſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction given by the Legate from his Holineſs, that troubleſom Quarrel is now brought to a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:55404:71"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict OF The Duke of
<hi>Novailles.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HIs Extraction is Illuſtrious, and of the ancient Nobility: the whole Family have ever been remarkable for their Fidelity, and conſtant Adherence to their Kings Intereſt. He is one of the four Captains of his Majeſties Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guards, and moſt commonly hath the ſole Command in the
<hi>Louvre,</hi> ſtill attending his Maſters perſon where-ever he is pleaſed to go; always riding in the Boot of the Kings Coach with the Baton in his <pb n="131" facs="tcp:55404:71"/>hand. He commands the Scotch Company under the White Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours. And although he is one of the moſt daring Souldiers in the Nation, and as valiant as any of theſe times; yet no man is endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with more Meekneſs or Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty then he is. He executes his employment with ſo much ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and content to all the world, that he is beloved and eſteemed by the whole Court: his very denials having ſo little of harſhneſs in them, that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſeldom go away diſcontented, though they loſe their Errand they came for. And ſo fair and obliging his nature is, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he can do a good office, it is performed ſo freely and nobly, either to friends, or even ſtrangers themſelves, that he lays a double tye of gratitude upon them, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as much from the manner, as the thing it ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:55404:72"/>
               <p>There is not a Noble-man in the Court that does not cover his friendſhip, nor any man ſo indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent as not to pay him a high re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. Nor is any man, though nere ſo great a ſtranger, denied acceſs to his preſence, if they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs themſelves but with civility to him. And yet is he ſevere e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough upon any occaſion of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, and will not ſuffer the leaſt diſorder either in the Kings fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or any place where his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand extends. He ſpeaks little, but very well to the purpoſe, and with a very great deal of ſolid Reaſon and Judgement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="Armand Charles de La Porte de La Meilleraye, duke of Mazarin"
                 type="character">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:55404:72"/>
               <head>THE Character or Pourtraict OF The Duke of <hi>Mazarine,</hi> AND <hi>de la Milleraye.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE is the ſon of the Marſhal <hi>de la Milleraye,</hi> Great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Ordnance; wherein he ſucceeds him, as well as in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>Bretagne,</hi> in quality of Lieutenant-General to the Queen-mother. He is a very vertuous Gentleman, a pious man: and it is ſaid, that in his <pb n="134" facs="tcp:55404:73"/>younger days he had a deſire of becoming a Religious. Frier. Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> looked upon him as the man to whom he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to leave his great Wealth, his Name, and his Arms; upon which condition he married his Neece. So that he is very rich on all ſides, and very potent; having beſides this, the Principality of <hi>Elſas,</hi> and the favour of the King, which is an advantage above all thoſe before mentioned. He is very ſtayd, ſpeaks little, and does every thing with a great deal of moderation: and though he is at this inſtant one of the greateſt and powerfulleſt Subjects in the world, yet is no whit the prouder, nor of a more difficult acceſs. He receives every body with a great deal of frankneſs and civility, and diſpatches the Kings affairs with all the conduct and exactneſs ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:55404:73"/>
               <p>He treated with the Princes of the <hi>Rhyne</hi> about many things of high importance, and hath gained a great deal of Credit and Reputation by his Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, having refuſed the Title of <hi>His Highneſs,</hi> which they would needs have given him, in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the Principality of <hi>Elſas.</hi> His late Buſineſs was, to cauſe the French Troops to paſs over a River on a Bridge of Boats, in the March towards the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Relief againſt the Grand Seignor.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
